Guide to the Merrill S. Hugo Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Merrill S. Hugo papers
1901-1960
1941-1960
SC0352
Hugo, Merrill S.
5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Hugo, a 1924 engineering graduate of Stanford and a Major with the United States Army Ordnance Department, joined the Stanford faculty in 1930 and served as director of the Gage Laboratory, School of Engineering.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of records the Gage Laboratory and the Stanford School of Engineering. Included are correspondence, research notes, procedural manuals, tolerance tables, technical reports, blueprints, schematics, transparencies, and diagrams.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Gage Laboratory.; Stanford University. School of Engineering. Faculty..; Engineering.; Ordnance.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - History of Gage Laboratory (Box 1)
    Gage Lab correspondence during the 1940's; Report of Gage Meeting in Philadelphia, 1943; History of Metrology; History of Gage Manufacturers; Stanford Ordiance School: Bibliography of Light Metals & Alloys
  - Operation of Laboratory (Box 2)
    Gage Laboratory procedures -Job Instruction: Planning Group Report; operation of Gage Laboratory
  - Professional Organizations/Education (Box 3)
    Gage Laboratory instructions (Hugo 's copy); Professional Engineering Organization: Education committee; California Society of Professional Engineers
  - Registration of Engineering Teachers (Box 4)
    California Society of Professional Engineers: correspondence, j ournals, committees
  - Gage Laboratory (Box 5)
    correspondence with Dept. of War: Office of Chief of Ordnance; inspection forms; Gage Tolerance Tables; Gage Transparencies & Diagrams
  - Gage Laboratory (Box 6)
    Blueprints & schematics; working Lab notes/tables/charts; research notes; History of Stanford Engineering: report to C.D. Marx, 1901; tolerance table
  - Stanford Engineering department (Box 7)
    Engineering professor's reprints; time schedules; newspaper/magazine clippi ngs; project reports; 35mm black and white slides: Gage Laboratory
  - Inspectors Manual for Macroetching, report no. 313.1/10 N.L. Read, 1941 (Box 8)
  - Directives of the Gage section; Industrial service Research & Engineering Division Ordnance Deparbnent (M.S. Hugo) (Box 8)
  - Directives of the Gage section; Industrial Service Researc..'1 & Engineering Division Ordnance Deparbnent (edition differs from previous entry) (Box 8)
  - Military Standard Gages, Snapf Plain, Adjustable MIL-STD-118 14 Jan~ry 1953 (Box 8)
  - Gage CK Worksheets] (1 black volume) (Box 8)
  - Military Standard Gages, Plug, Plain, Cylindrical (GO) MIL-STD-110 25 January 1951 (Box 8)
  - Gage Laboratory No. GL-20 (laboratory notebook bound) (Box 8)
  - Military standard Gages, Ring, Plain (GO) MIL-STD-112 25 January 1951 (Box 8)
  - Military Standard Gage Inspection MIL-STD-120 12 December 1950 (2 copies) (Box 8)
  - Quality Control with DoAll Gages and Gage Instruments: a Handbook of Scientific Inspection (Box 8)
  - Manual Gage Inspection: prepared under the direction of the Chief of Ordnance U. S. Army (Box 8)
  - Ordnance Inspection Handbook on Gage Preliminary Edition September 1944 ORD-M608-5-SEC. 800 (Box 8)
  - section 800: Gage Inspection Methods, 1 July 1945 p.801-1205 (Box 8)